Kieran:
So Jane – you’ll be off to Denmark soon to do your work placement.
Jane:
Yes, I’m really looking forward to it and I’ve just started packing up all
my books to put in storage.
Kieran:
Well, I hope they don’t get spoilt.
Jane:
It’s OK – my grandfather works in a bookshop and he told me how
to pack them.
Kieran:
Oh,
that’s helpful.
Jane:
He says you have to support the spine otherwise the paper can come away
from the cover.
Kieran:
Yeah – that’s obvious.
Jane:
He also told me to pack them flat in the box not on their side – again
because they can bend and if you leave them like that for, say, a
year, it’s quite hard to get them back to their normal shape.
Kieran:
Well, it’s pretty clear that ruins them,
but a lot of people just can’t be bothered to protect their books.
Jane:
He always says it’s such a shame that publishers don’t use better-quality
paper.
Kieran:
It’s the acid in the paper that causes the problem, isn’t it?
Jane:
Yeah – that’s why old books go yellow.
You know some of the books my grandfather’s given me are like that
already.
Kieran:
Oh .
.
Jane:
I should dump them really if they’re going to deteriorate further,
but I’d feel bad.
They’ll always remind me of him.
He’s quite a collector, you know.
Kieran:
Well, if they’re important to you .
.
Jane:
Yeah – I’d regret just throwing them away.
Kieran:
You know, maybe it’s because I was taught to treasure books .
.
but I hate seeing students force open the pages – of paperbacks.
They press so hard they end up breaking the spine.
Jane:
I know,
but unfortunately, paperbacks aren’t designed to last a long time
and people know that.
Hardbacks aren’t quite as weak.
Kieran:
Yeah, they’re different, I suppose.
But I still don’t think people value hardbacks like they used to.
Jane:
Well, they aren’t decorative, are they, like other objects.
Plus, nowadays, people don’t keep them out on shelves as much as they used
to.
Kieran:
That’s such a pity.
When I visit someone – if they have, say, a colourful book on a
table, it’s the first thing I’m drawn to.
Jane:
I agree – and book covers can be a work of art in themselves.
Some are really eye-catching.
Kieran:
I’ve always been taught to handle books carefully.
If you watch someone take a book off a shelf, well, they usually do
it wrong.
Jane:
Ah, my grandfather says, you should put your hand right over the top of
the book .
.
or if you can’t do that, pull the other books on the shelf aside
so that you can hold the whole cover.
Kieran:
When did you learn all this?
Jane:
He watched me pull a heavy book off the shelf when I was small,
and it fell on the floor and broke apart.
Kieran:
Oh dear!
Jane:
I can still remember it!
Kieran:
You know what I really like?
Jane:
What?
Kieran:
The smell of new books.
Jane:
Me too.
Kieran:
My parents used to laugh at me when I was a kid
because I loved putting books up to my nose.
Almost as much as reading them!
Jane:
New books aren’t cheap, though, are they?
Kieran:
I guess we’re lucky we can buy them.
Jane:
My grandfather stocks second-hand books as well as new ones
and they don’t smell quite as good.
Kieran:
I’d love to have a bookshop like your grandfather.
What’s it like?
Jane:
Well, it’s quite big – it’s got two floors and an attic,
and he stocks all kinds of books really.
Kieran:
I guess he treasures things like first editions and other rare books.
Jane:
Yeah – you might think he’d keep those in the attic or somewhere.
Kieran:
.
so they’d be hidden?
Jane:
Yeah.
But he likes people to know that he has them.
So, he puts them out in the shop but makes sure you need a
ladder to get them.
Kieran:
Right.
That would prevent any thefts!
Jane:
Uhuh.
Kieran:
Does he stock books for children?
Jane:
He does.
He particularly likes to encourage kids to read;
he always says that he used to sit under the stairs as a child with a pile of books
and read them all.
Kieran:
Is that where he keeps them, then?
Jane:
Not exactly – he’s got a dedicated area on the ground floor with cushions
so that parents can enter with their toddlers, go there
and spend some time reading to them.
Kieran:
Oh cool.
Jane:
And then there’s a place for pushchairs by the front door.
And a café if anyone needs refreshments.
Kieran:
That’s good to know.
Jane:
As I said, it’s a big shop and there’s a storage area out the
back as well.
Kieran:
Oh, what does he keep there?
Books he wants to throw away?
Jane:
He hardly ever throws anything away – he just leaves unwanted books by the
front door for customers to take.
Kieran:
Well,
that’s very nice.
Jane:
Yeah – and books people or institutions have requested, they all go at the
far end.
Kieran:
Oh.
Jane:
He thinks it’s best to keep these out of the main shopping area as they’re boxed
and new.
Kieran:
Did you get your coursebooks from him?
Jane:
Naturally.
He stocks books for a lot of the colleges.
He used to keep these books on the first floor,
but now there’s a new university in my hometown, he’s moved them downstairs to
attract the students.
They’re actually part of the coffee shop, on low shelves all around it.
Kieran:
Pretty central then.
You’ll have to take me there some time!